in Estonia the minimum wage is 4
в Эстонии минимальная зарплата в 4 по
times higher than a teacher's salary in
раза выше чем зарплата учителя в
Pskov Tell me what products in
Пскове Расскажи мне какие продукты в
Estonia cost 4 times more than in
Эстонии стоят в 4 с по раза дороже чем в
Russia Hello Hello Where are you
России Здравствуйте Здравствуйте Вы
from I understand from Moscow and to Moscow Where did you
откуда Я из Москвы понял а в Москву Куда
come from
приехали из
St. Petersburg and it is not clear to you whether it is Estonia or
Питера а по вам непонятно то ли Эстония
Ukraine Estonia support Ukraine
Толи Украина Эстония поддерживай Украину
There is a VPN so that Russia and Ukraine
Там VPN стал чтобы Россия и Украина мне
come across me and I understand because otherwise Only
попадалась а я понял бо иначе Только
Estonians come across ours oh great I
эстонцы попадаются наши ой класс Эстонию
love Estonia 9 years were in camps and in camps I fell asleep
люблю 9 лет в лагерях были а в лагерях
pioneer and where were you us Narva
усна ла пионерски а где были усь нарова
understood Well, maybe you were in Pärnu
понял Ну а может были в Пярну у нас
somewhere on the
где-то на
coast we were taken to Tallinn once but I do
побережье один раз в талин нас возили но
n't remember that Narva is good
это уже не помню вот у Нарву хорошо
Very in children's camps and then we didn't
Очень в детских лагерях а потом уже не
come
приезжали
No then I really wanted to but I didn't
Нет потом очень хотел но не
come Well, it's
приезжал Ну и
worth it Well, let's go sometime we need to
стоит Да не ну съездим как-нибудь надо
see these old places
это старые места посмотреть
there are children to remember look I
там дет вспомнить есть смотри я в России
have Baikal in Russia for example yes you can
есть Байкал например да вот там
relax there it's all clear but we need to
отдохнуть можно это всё понятно но надо
go to Estonia  all the same,
съездить в Эстонию всё-таки детские
I'll get out sometime to see the children's places,
места посмотреть всё-таки я выберусь
I'm serious I don't
как-нибудь я вот серьёзно Не
recommend it, it's better to go all over
рекомендую лучше ездите сначала всю
Russia first, otherwise your life won't be enough, that's exactly it, that's exactly it, that's exactly it, that's exactly what the
Россию так жизни не хватит вот вот вот
calculation is that
как раз да Как раз на это и расчёт что
you won't have enough life, you won't get to Estonia Why are
вам не хватит жизни вы в Эстонию не
you so Inhospitable,
доедете А что вы такие Не гостеприимные
we invite everyone to our place, to be honest, don't invite,
мы к себе всех зовём честно говоря вот
don't invite and don't come That's how
не зовите не зовите и не приезжайте Вот
we've already seen That's
как-то так мы уже видели как
better to go to Baikal, honestly, that's not it, that's
Вот лучше на Байкал честно мы не так мы
not it, we'll come for tourism purposes That's exactly it,
не так мы в туристических целях приедем
honestly, we're not tourists No,
Вот вот вот честно нас не туристами Да
that's not carcasses, no way That's just no way What's your
не это не тушками никак Вот просто никак
name, excuse me,
Вас как зовут извини
Jonas Jonas, I'm
йонас йонас меня
Andrejs, I heard your personal
андрейс я услышал ваше личное
opinion, but it seems to me
мнение но мне кажется
that's how it is from all the people of Estonia, we and so
вот так от всего народа Эстонии мы и так
on, well, you shouldn't say that's your
далее ну не стоит говорить это ваше
personal opinion I heard Everything is clear,
личное мнение Я я услышал Всё понятно
everything We treat you normally When
всё Мы к вам нормально относимся Когда
you were
вы
there, you were with us in
там вот вы у нас с сорокового года в
Estonia from 1940 to 1991, and to be
Эстонии были по девяносто первый так и
honest, I don't want to, I
честно говоря не хочется
want to, for some of the people
чтобы ещё хочется чтобы часть людей
who remained from that time to go
которые остались от того времени уехали
back to Russia  That would be good Well, oh,
назад в Россию Это было бы хорошо Ну ой
listen, you are driving away your own citizens, that is not
слушайте вы своих граждан прогоняете это
at all nice, not really, they are citizens,
вообще некрасиво не совсем это граждане
they are the heirs of the occupation regime
это Наследники оккупационного режима
who became
которые стали
citizens, how can it be that you are not ashamed, are you not
гражданами как же как же вам то не
ashamed? These are people who
стыдно во не стыдно Это ж люди с вами
live together with you, and you are directly
живут вместе а вы вы прямо вот кого-то
calling someone not citizens, ours, look at
называете не граждана наши смотрите
our grandfathers, my great-grandfather was there, Uh, in
наших дедов у меня прадед был Ээ в
1940, when the Soviets came, they sent him
сороковом году когда пришли советы его
to
в
something like this, now I will tell you what it was called,
такое сейчас скажу как это называлась
Sandarmokh, what is it? There
сандармох
was such a camp, where in
что это такое Это лагерь такой был Где в
Russia in the
России на
north, in Siberia, Nadezhda No, that is not Siberia, I
севере в Сибири Наде Нет это не Сибирь
think it is somewhere in Karelia, that is
это по-моему где-то Карелия вот
there, well, I don’t know, I can’t say here
там ну не знаю тут не могу сказать
Well, maybe yes, my great-grandfather
Ну наве на может быть да прадед там
died there, my grandmother was
погиб бабушка э была
shot, my grandmother was shot for anti-
расстреляна бабушка расстреляна за Анти
Soviet activities, yes, his daughter is
советскую деятельность Да его дочка это
his daughter, his daughter, yes, yes, my grandmother was
его дочка его дочка да так Бабушка была
shot for anti-Soviet
расстреляна за антисоветской
activities, and my mother, my mother lived and worked, well, she
деятельность А мама мама жила работала
worked, where in
Да ну класс работала Где в детском
kindergarten, well,
садике Ну и
that’s great,
класс такая
sorry, in
Извините в
Russia Well, first of all, from the cartoon, let’s
России Ну во-первых из мультика давайте
live in peace, and secondly  there is a saying that
жить дружно а во-вторых поговорка такая
whoever remembers the past will lose his eye, you know, yes, yes, I
кто старые помянет тому глаз вон знаете
wonder how this saying works: whoever
Интересно как работает эта поговорка кто
sings the old one will lose his eye if
старая поет кому глаз вон если
Russia still makes some kind of claims to all other countries about the
Россия до сих пор ко всем другим странам
past, what
даёт какие-то претензии прошлых что там
were you in the Russian Empire? Let's
вы были в Российской империи Давайте
now have to grab this, it's not the old one who remembers.
теперь мы должны зах это не есть старая
Who says that we
помянет Кто такое говорит что мы вас
will seize you? Well, many Russians,
будем захватывать Ну многие русский и в
including your leadership, say that
том числе ваше руководство говорит что
these are all territories of the Russian Empire and
это всё территории Российской империи и
Ukraine and Estonia and
Украина и Эстония и
Finland. Who from the leadership of my country
Финляндия Кто из руководства моей страны
said such a thing lately? When in an
такое говорил последнее время Ко когда в
interview I looked, I don't remember this cart.
интервью Я посмотрел не помню это воз
Even if he said this, it seems to me that there
Даже если он это сказал мне кажется там
was nothing there that we will attack you now
не было ничего что мы сейчас на вас
and you are not there. He doesn't say we will attack.
нападём и вас нет Он не говорит нападём
He says that these are our lands,
Он говорит это наши земли
historically, historically, our lands, everything, and
исторически исторически наши земли всё и
live there, you were let go, everything is fine.
живите там вас отпустили всё хорошо А
Now tell me what does it mean that these are your
теперь скажите что значит это ваш
historical lands when the territory of
исторический земли когда территория
Estonia became your historical lands?
Эстонии стала вашими историческими
Well, when the Swedes
землями Ну когда шведам
got beat up in what year in the
наваляли каком
700s, I don't remember what year, but you have a
в700 не помню каком году а то есть у вас
history of the
история
year, you consider every land
года вы вы каждую злю землю считаете
yours from the moment it is convenient for you, yes, Describe to
своей с того момента когда вам удобно
me if I'm
да Опишите мне если я не
wrong. You are wrong. Tell me.  Let's
прав Вы не правы Расскажите Давайте
because look from time immemorial this
потому что смотрите из покон веков эта
Earth was the land of
Земля была земля
Estonia No this is the Land of Estonia was the Swedes if the
Эсто Нет это Земля Эсто была шведы бы
Swedes came here the same way you came This is the Land of E if you look at the order was Where was I don't know this is your story I haven't really heard about Yori but I know that on the Narva River there is a Swedish fortress on one side I was in it this
шведская крепость Я в ней был вот этот
castle Yes and on the other side there is the
замок Да а с другой стороны стоит
Ivangorod fortress I even know the
ивангородская крепость Я даже знаю
history of its creation when these White
историю её создания когда вот эти Белого
Horse There they cut the corners and so on No well
коня Там кутки порезали и так далее Не
look you you are talking about the Swedes
ну смотрите вы вы вы про
there Swedish here Russian
Швед там шведская тут русская
you take a specific period the 10th century is the
вы берте конкретный период X век это
same as for example
также как например
Take the 10th century Moscow and for example the
Возьмите X век Москва и например
10th century Moscow Generally different Moscows really
X век Москва Вообще разные Москвы правда
absolutely there are Mongols Yes here in short it is
абсолютно там монголы Да тут короче
generally unclear who so
вообще непонятно уже кто так вот
look initially Estonia Yes it was the
смотрите изначально Эстония Да это была
land of Estonia when Kale pok Da descended to this
земля Эсто когда кале пок Да сошл на эту
land he said he threw
землю он сказал он кинул
Kavi who is this This is the hero of our epic the son of
Кави кто это Это Герой нашего эпоса сын
Kaliva And this is some kind of mythical
калива А это какое-то мифическое
creature bo like Rurik Like you like
существо бо типа как Рюрик У вас как У
you  Rurik is our kapok, but that's not what I'm talking about,
вас Рюрик у нас капок да я не про это я
he threw this big stone, it's there, and he
он кинул вот этот камень большой там он
said that it would be your land,
есть вот и сказал это будет ваша Земля
and since then our ancestors have lived there, we
да и с тех пор наши предки жили там мы
Estonians, we didn't come from anywhere, we've lived here since
эсты ни откуда не пришли мы жили тут из
time immemorial, look at theology, and
покон веков посмотри теология Да даёт
I don't argue. Great, don't rush, don't rush, the fact that
ещё я не спорю Здорово Не спеши не спеши
you came and went later, and so
то что вы потом пришли тут ушли И так
on, doesn't give you the right to say
дальше это не даёт вам право говорить
that such and such lands are yours, moreover, the
что такие-то ваши земли больше
city of Leningrad, also known as
того город Ленинград он же
St. Petersburg, yes, these are not your
санкт-петербург да Это не ваши
historical lands, so these are our Estonian
исторические земли так это наш эстонский
lands, and yours, yes, look, the entire
земли А ваши Да все смотри ээ вся
Leningrad region is the land of the Finno-
Ленинградская область это земли фино
Ugric peoples, the Estonians were a little bit,
угорских народов были эсты чуть мере
why is Lake Peipus
Почему озеро Чудское
called unknown because the people were a little bit, the people were a
называется неизве потому что народ чуть
little bit, in the annals they were doing weird things, or something, the people were a little bit, these are the Estonians,
народ чуть ээ в летописи чудили чудили
we
что ли народ чуть это и есть эсты мы
are a little bit, so the lake is sensitive, you see
есть чуть поэтому озеро чуткое ты видишь
where the lake is sensitive,
где чуткое
this is all Our lands are not a Russian
озеро это всё Наши земли не русское
lake, so not Russian, but Peipus, because I'll
озеро так не русское а Чудское потому
say a little bit, the bay is Finnish and the
что чу больше скажу залив то финский и
Gulf of Finland  Correct Because here
Финский залив Правильно Потому что тут
a little and there the Finns were straw yes Absolutely
чуть а там фины были соломи да Абсолютно
right in general Listen cool cool you're
верно вообще Слушай круто круто ты
finally starting on almost everything
наконец-то начинаешь по почти всё
inserted atno almost everything inserted on the
вставило атно почти всё вставило на
shelf Yes Gulf of Finland And how many
полочке Да Финский залив А сколько
how many population in Estonia now e one and
сколько населения в Эстонии сейчас э
a half million according to the census yes but
полтора миллиона по переписи было да но
in fact now a million because
фактически сейчас Миллион потому что
many are mobile They live in other
многие мобильные Они проживают в других
countries this is less than in my area
странах это меньше чем у меня в райне
what well but yes But we have a monoethnic
что ну зато да Зато у нас моноэтническое
state we have land Estonia live e
государство у нас земля Эсто живут э у
in your area you don't understand what kind of
вас в районе у вас не понятно какое
state Yes there are Tatars Mongols now
государство Да там татары монголы сейчас
Uzbeks Tajiks Chechens Well there all
узбеки таджики чеченцы Ну там все
Saint Petersburg national state yes that is
санкт-петербур национальное государст да
you don't have Russians here until
то есть у вас нету у русских вот до сих
now as Russians like them a people who have
пор как русские как и они народ который
not found their own state there are such
не обрёл своего государство есть такие
peoples Kurds yet Yes have not found their own
народы курды ещё Да не обрели своё
state but at least they have
государство но у них хотя бы есть
Listen, I'm sorry I didn't really record
Слушай извини я не очень зафиксировал
your name Sorry it's unusual for me
твоё имя Прости оно необычное для меня
so I'm sorry
поэтому извини
sorry Russian analogue Ivan is like Ivan
извини русский аналог Иван это как Иван
in Russia in these
в России в этих
Ioan in  Europe ys is the same church
Иоан в Европе йс это этот же церковный
analogue of Estonian Well if I
аналог эстонского Ну если я тебя буду
call you Ivan you will be upset Well this is
называть Иваном ты расстроишься Ну это
different this is completely
другое это совсем
different there is Pablo there is Pavel Yes there are
друго есть Пабло есть Павел Да есть
others yes
другие да
Or it is complicated also Juan here is Ivan in Spain
Или сложно также Хуан вот Иван в Испании
- this is
- это
Juan here is John
Хуан вот Иоан
Johann here is Johann Sebastian baz This is the same
иоган вот иоган Себастьян баз Это тот же
Jonas but
йонас но
German Listen nose wanted to know
немецкий Слушай нос хотел у тебя узнать
one thing from you To be honest I saw
одну вещь Вот честно скажу вот увидел
that a person from the Baltics
что человек из Прибалтики Прибалтики
When they say Baltics the Baltics are an
когда говорят Прибалтика - это
occupation name Russian we
оккупационного название российское мы
call a person from the Baltic countries That's how you
назва человек из стран балтии Вот так
should say Well you're good I understand you nose
надо говорить Ну ты хорошо я нос тебя
but please don't retrain me
понял но меня пожалуйста не переучивать
I will try not to use the word
Я постараюсь не употреблять э слова
Baltics This believe me that
Прибалтика Это поверь мне что
in reality I do not offend This I do not offend we do not like this
яве я не обижаю Это я не обижаю нам не
we do not like I will
нравится это нам не нравится я
try Let's accept But if if
постараюсь Давайте принять Но если если
suddenly it slips through then do not be offended I will not be
вдруг проскочит значит не обижайся я не
offended Sola
обижусь Сола
Listen here they tell a story such that
Слушай тут рассказывают историю такую
your
вот ваши
countries can be called the Baltic
страны можно их назвать балтийские
tigers I
тигры Почему
don't know why tigers are so ardent against the
тигры не знаю та ярые такие против
Russians it does not matter Okay everything is not
русских не суть Ладно всё не об этом
your countries disconnected from
ваши страны отключились от
this energy
это энергии
system and here the Ukrainians
системы и тут укра
show some strange
знани показывают какие-то странные
graphs where prices for
графики где цены выросли на
electricity doubled, they lie, I don't know,
электроэнергию в два раза врут не знаю в
doubled, I didn't feel it, we didn't have any
два раза я не ощути у нас вообще не было
price changes at all, from this he
изменения цены из
also wrote here You know, a
этого там ещё написал Вот это знаешь
Ukrainian blogger, there is Shari, a
украинский блогер есть шари такой
Spanish blogger He has been living in Spain for
испанский блогер Он в Испании живёт лет
20 years or so Yes, but he is from Ukraine, he is
20 или сколько Да но он из Украины он
for Ukraine against Zelensky, but for
тот за Украину против Зеленского но за
Ukraine, this
Украину этол
Ukrainian one, that's who you
украинский
were He ran away, I understand Because
вот ти был Он убежал я понял Потому что
he was tried He ran away from justice and is
его судили Он убежал от правосудия и
hiding Exactly Exactly This is his nose, you
прячется Точно Точно Вот это он нос ты
saw his wife She also has a block, his wife
его жену Видел у неё тоже есть блок жена
is Olya, she looks like a man, m, a man, no, no, no,
это Оля она на мужика похожа м мужика у
such a
не у не такие подпи такую
Thai woman, Okay, okay There is no accounting for taste,
тайку ла Ладно ладно О вкусах не спорим
in short, prices Look, I don't know where this
короче цены Смотри я не знаю откуда этот
ball came from, in short, I found this, yes Nothing has changed with our
шарик короче нашёл это да У нас ничего с
prices,
ценами не
I understand And he also wrote that
изменилось я понял И ещё написал что
somewhere in one of your countries,
где-то вот в одном из ваших государств
some kind of plant closed, a
закрылся какой-то
city that strangely forms something, they are
завод городо странно образующий что-то
already writing about the Volkswagen plant  3
это про завод Volkswagen пишут уже 3
months and all the Russians say something to me They say
месяца и мне все русские что-то Говорят
this in Germany that the Volkswagen plant
это в Германии что завод Volkswagen
closed and in short there it's all some kind of
закрылся и короче там всё это какой-то
nonsense I don't know no no not there exactly I
бред Я не знаю нене не там именно вот
almost said sorry in the Baltics in
чуть не сказал извини в Прибалтике в
Latvia in Lithuania not in Estonia I remember exactly
Латвии в Литве не в Эстонии точно помню
in Latvia and Lithuania the plant closed there
в Латвии и в Литве закрылся завод там
such comments from the financial director
такие комментарии финансового директора
that like prices went up here's what to
что типа вот цены повысились вот что
do
делать
And I'm just wondering now it's clear there are a
И мне просто интересно сейчас понятно
lot of fakes now you can have
фейков куча сейчас можно
them in Estonia was small We would have already
их на Эстония маленькая было Мы бы уже
known this Maybe somewhere something in Latvia and
это знали Может где-то что-то в Латвии и
Lithuania I'm not in the know it's unlikely that something so
Литве я не в курсе вряд ли что-то такое
serious that we would know about it and you yourself
серьёзное что мы бы знали снас а сам ты
were in Narvi Where in
был в у нарви Где в
U and
у а
why not me Listen we have I don't know we have
зачем не я Слушай у нас Я не знаю у нас
Pärnu there is this resort everyone goes to Pärnu
Пярну есть вот это курорт все в Пярну
Yes here is a ski resort
едут Да вот отпи горнолыжный курорт у
we have at least a ski resort So
нас хоть горнолыжный это
you saw yes we have
Так вы же видели да у нас
Pere Otto Yes there are small differences in
пере Отто Да там небольшие есть перепады
altitude there is even a bun like yes we
высот как раз есть даже булк типа да мы
go skiing and there in the summer we go there all the time
ездим катаемся и там летом постоянно мы
too on skis They come on skis
ездим тоже на лыжах Приезжают на лыжах
on roller skates  these are the skis And on roller skates they
на роликах вот эти лыжи А на роликах там
train there Our Estonian national team
тренируется там у наша Эстонская сборная
trains The Olympic team in the summer they go
тренируется Олимпийская летом они ездят
skiing
на лыжах
with wheels plus they go to Finland to
с колёсиками плюс ездят в Финляндию на
train on indoor tracks here and in the winter
тренироваться трассы вот а в зимний
now we were there for Christmas Yes, they
период сейчас вот мы были на Рождество
just won't
Да отпи вообще просто не
wake up at all listen well cool well I'm very
проснутся слуша ну круто вот ну я очень
happy because they tell us that
рад потому что нам-то рассказывают что у
you don't have anything there at all omto
вас там ничего нет вобще омто
this is very cool I'm very
это очень круто я очень
happy Well because really from the summer camps I
ра Ну пото что реально с лет лагерей я
say so in Estonia I have
так говор в Эстонии мне
such How much are the salaries now for example
тако Сколько сейчас зарплаты например
teachers here in Moscow and St. Petersburg
учителя вот у вас в Москве и в Питере
Russia Listen I wasn't interested But I'll
России Слушай я не интересовался Но
say that they are high now everyone says
скажу что высокие вот сейчас все говорят
that doctors Uchebnye low for
что враче Учите низкие за
T Recently there was some topic that they have
Т Недавно была какая-то тема что у них
some kind of official salary there It seems to be
там какие-то зарплата официальная вроде
Some kind of small but with allowances
Небольшая какая-то но с надбавками
here and there they come out Very cool and plus
туда-сюда выходят Очень круто и плюс
additions all the same they are doctors how do they
добавок все же врачи они как они же
work there half a day in the clinic in
работают там полдня в поликлинике в
this they they don't have an eight-hour
этой у них у них не восьмичасовой
work day and so they work half a day in the
рабочий день и вот они полдня в
clinic  and then they go to a paid
поликлинике а потом идут в платную
job at night and there they consult someone yes that is what And
рабо ночью е там консультируют кого-то
I don't know about this,
да то есть что А это я не знаю с этим
here's how you count it I'll smoke I don't mind I wo
вот как вы его счита я закурю не против
n't via the
мне не будет через
Internet but here's how you think I'm
интернет а вот как вы считаете мне
interested in yours You seem adequate, we
интересно ваш Вот вы вроде адекватные с
can talk yes How do you think
вами можно поговорить да Как вы считаете
where is the best standard of living in Russia or in
где лучший уровень жизни в России или в
Europe so I've been to Europe many times uh
Европе так в Европе я был много раз
Let's tell you from my example
э ээ Давайте из своего примера расскажу
Yes, let's say
Да там допустим
Paris 2007 or eight
Париж 2007 или вось
We were talking with a colleague at work I
год Общались мы с коллегой по работе я
came there to work he He was
приехал туда работать он Он моего
about my status not about my
примерно статуса не примерно моего
status So we got to
статуса был Вот и мы что-то с ним
talking
разговорились
He says I earn 2500 euros I
Он говорит Я зарабатываю 2500 евро Я
say well that's cool he says well not so
говорю ну круто он говорит ну не так
cool because I give half to
круто потому что я половину отдаю
Zar in the center of Paris and so on then
Зар в центре Парижа и так далее потом
further I myself went to restaurants there went out and drank
дальше я уже сам ходил по ресторанам там
something
ушёл пил что-то
else saw the prices for these coffee the prices there are
ещё видел цены на эти на кофе цены там
completely for Russia this is in the center of Paris
совершенно для Росси это в центре Парижа
Yes this is in the center of Paris Well this is
Да это в центре Парижа Ну это
touristy here Then we went to the
туристически тут Потом мы поехали на
outskirts we had business there and we decided
окраину у нас там было дело и мы решили
with my Russian  colleague
с моим русским коллегой сигареты
ran out of cigarettes go buy and that's where my
кончились пойти купить и вот там у меня
opinion about Europe completely changed because we
э мнение о Европе потому что вот Мы
worked there was such a small
работали там был такой маленький
microdistrict there are such
микрорайон там такие домишки
individual two-story houses Very beautiful
индивидуальные двухэтажные Очень красиво
Very cool but across the highway across the
Очень круто а вот через шоссе через
road there are these concrete
дорогу там вот эти вот бетонные
multi-story buildings and we go into some kind of
многоэтажки и мы заходим в какой-то типа
store and there are such guys sitting in the parking lot
магазин какой-то и там сидят на парковке
like
такие пацанчики как
in Russia such you understand about the World Cup speech
в Росси таки такие понимаешь о ЧМ говор
Yes Tol these are the same but of Arab
Да Толь это те же самые но арабской
appearance that's the main thing that I will tell
внешности вот а главно что буду расска
was wild in Spain we were on so
была дичь в Испании мы были на так
look not just your expert opinion
смотри не просто Ваше экспертное мнение
Where is the standard of living higher in Russia or in
Где выше уровень жизни в России или в
Europe let's go from the very me of
Европе давай пойду с самого ме из
but and here they had
но и вот у них у них
they have all died a long time ago a
был они уже все умерли очень давно
familiar friend de Fin he came to them
знакомый друг де Фин он к ним приезжал
twice a year for mom and
два раза в год на День рождения мамы и
dad's birthday and so we always met there
папы и вот мы там всегда встречались
when u
когда у
got married and this n
женился и этот н
came different
приезжал разно
credit you hand over the old one they pay
зачёт старую сдаёшь
extra he Was in the construction
доплачивают он Был в строительном
business Well some simple
бизнесе Ну какой-то простой
worker after he went on  pension he
рабоч после то как он вышел на пенсию он
already stopped changing cars started
уже перестал менять машины начал
coming once a year moved into an apartment
приезжать раз в год переехал в квартиру
and then my Tes sat with him and they started
а дальше мой Тесь с ним сел и они начали
talking about their
говорить о своих
pensions only nose Wash like a Ukrainian he
пенсиях только нос Мойте как украинец он
was sh yly he said here my
был щ ушлый он сказал вот у меня
rent is so much cigarettes so much food so much
квартплата столько сигареты столько еда
water so much This is so much And
столько вода столько Это столько А у
you like that had a big pension but
тебя как у того была большая пенсия но
prices are different As a result it turned out that my
цены другие В итоге Выяснилось что мой
father-in-law is three times richer than
тесть в три раза богаче чем
Fin I answered the question super cool
Фин Я ответил на вопрос супер крутая
story now tell me your expert
история теперь скажите своё экспертное
opinion where is the highest standard of living in Russia
мнение где высший уровень жизни в России
or in Europe just without an example you have
или в Европе просто без примеро имеете
let's what do you mean by standard of living
давайте что вы имеете под уровнем жизни
what can I do
что я могу сделать
or purchasing power for my
или покупательная способность на свою
pay here is a teacher in Russia and a
запла вот учительница в России и
teacher in Europe yes Who is richer I don't
учительница в Европе да Кто богаче Я не
know about teachers I'll tell you now
знаю про учителей я вам сейчас
about the standard of living I'll say this my
скажу про уровень жизни скажу так моё
clear absolute opinion that again with an
чёткое абсолютное мнение что опять же на
example I can tell that in the USA and in
примере могу расказать что в США и в
Russia it is much cooler than in Europe
России гораздо круче чем в Европе потому
because we worked in Spain in Malaga and
что мы работали в Испании в малаге и
I came my American colleagues with
приехали я мои американские Коллеги с
us some Romanian woman was And that's when
нами какая-то румынка была И вот когда
we decided to eat  somewhere after
мы решили поесть где-то после
ddx to celebrate the project we couldn't find a place to
ддх отметить проект мы не нашли место
eat it
где поесть это всё
was all closed and that was such
было всё закрыто и вот это была такая
nonsense the American woman tells me I can
дичь мне американка говорит я могу 24
order pizza mitsu 24 hours a day
часа в сутки заказать пиццу мицу что
anything anywhere to eat I say me too
угодно где угодно поесть Я говорю Я тоже
I can buy a car in Moscow what
я могу у себя в Москве купить хоть
city were you in
машину это вы в каком городе были в
what city were you in
каком городе были в
Malaga in Spain Malaga couldn't
малаге в Испании малаге не смогли
eat after 10:00 pm and
покушать после 10:00 вечера и пиццу
order pizza No we had a hard time
заказать Нет мы там с трудом на
finding some restaurant on the coast where they
побережье нашли какой-то ресторанчик где
let us in we quickly
ээ допустили мы там по-быстренькому
celebrated there in 15 minutes and ran away and that
отметили за 15 минут и разбежались и
was such nonsense
была такая дичь
and that's an interesting question uh For me
и это вот интересный вопрос ээ Для меня
yes Because I studied at Tartu
да Потому что я в тартуского
University and I
университете да учился и как раз у меня
specialize in sociology uh sociologist - This is
социолог специализация э социолог - Это
not the one that uh does public surveys
не тот что э общественные опросы делает
But the study of social trends of different
А изучение общественных тенденций разных
And so on And so we had just
И так дальше И вот у нас было как раз
Uh what is it in Russian the subject
Ээ как это по-русски предмет
migration
миграционные
processes that semester was going and I remember
процессы вот семестр как шёл и я помню
how the teacher very clearly
как раз преподавателя очень чётко он
said look you can juggle
сказал смотрите можно жонглировать
economic indicators some
экономическими показателями какими-то
examples
примерами
but migration processes are always an
но миграционные процессы всегда есть
indicator of
индикатором
where it is worse and where it is better if the migration of the
того где хуже и где лучше если миграция
population goes from point A to point B
населения идёт с точки А в точки б
It means that at point B the standard of living is
Значит в точке б уровень жизни
higher if the opposite does not happen then it means less
выше если наоборот не идёт значит меньше
I look from this point of view yes from
я смотрю с точки зрения этого да из
Russia to Europe a huge number of
России в Европу огромная количество
people are moving millions just yes And
людей переселяется миллионы просто да А
from Europe to
из Европы в
Russia zero How can
Россию ноль Как можно объяснить тогда
this phenomenon be explained then if not by the fact that in Europe the
этот феномен если не тем что в Европе
standard of living is higher and people are
уровень жизни выше и люди туда
going there Well this is old this is
едут Ну это ж старая вот это вот в
good in Europe it is great in Europe my
Европе хорошо в Европе классно у меня
relatives moved to the States lived on
родственники переезжали в Штаты жили на
Manny they lived there for some time
манни пожили они там какое-то врем
looked at all the
посмотрели на весь
mess how long they lived a year a little less
бардак сколько они жили год чуть меньше
Well and to hell they came back well these are those
Ну и к чёрту вернулись обратно ну это те
who did not
кто не
settle down no they settled down they are
обустроились нет они обустроились у них
all good Well in a
всё хорошо Ну за
year for them everything is fine for them not in a
год вот у них вот у них всё хорошо не за
year it is like the children did not even have time to go to school
год это даже типа не успели в школу
and so on No no there there
пойти дети и так дальше Да не не там там
everything is great there they are
там всё классно там их
just The key thing was that their
просто Ключевая была штука что их по
nephew could not enter
признаку племянник не смог поступить в
this
этот
most famous technological school due to their nationality
самых известный технологический
Michigan Massachusetts Mi Masks
мичиганский массачусетский ми маски
Masaki Yes, he had
масаки Да вот мит у него были
all of them Yes, they just told him them Just then
все Да ему просто им Просто потом в
openly You are Russian And who is
открытую сказали Вы русские А кто
Russian by nationality they didn’t take him
русский по национальности не взяли его
Yes And what about other Russians studying at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs I do
да А как же в МИД другие русские учатся
n’t know how other
я не знаю как другие
Russians Secha Te I’ll tell you That was a long time ago
русские сеча те скажу Вот это давно уже
but it seems to me after the fourteenth
было но мне кажется после четырнадцатого
not after the fourteenth naturally
не после четырнадцатого естественно
Now I’ll even try to find out to you
Сейчас я тебе даже попытаюсь выяснить
if NNN then it’s probably somewhere It
если ННН то это где-то наверное Мне
seems to me sixteenth seventeenth
кажется шестнадцатый семнадцатый
eighteenth you are somewhere I just personally
восемнадцатый вы где-то Я просто я лично
know people who are Russian from Russia and
знаю людей которые русские из России и
study at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and in the sixteenth and in the
учатся в МИД и в шестнадцатом и в
seventeenth year they entered with well cool I’m
семнадцатом году поступали с ну круто я
telling you a story from my family
тебе рассказываю историю из своей семьи
absolutely really
абсолютно реально
no At the same time
нет При этом
they are quite wealthy people, let’s even
они довольно обеспеченные люди даже
say wealthy
скажем так обеспеченные
people and after they were
люди и вот после того как им вот это вот
told this that it was precisely on the basis of nationality the
сказали что именно по национально
guys said and immediately left and
признаку сказа ребята и сразу уехали а
what about Man there New York Branch Russians
как же там Ман же ньюйорк бранч русские
live they go to university to sing
живут они в университет поть
gu Well  I just have one like this Wait
гу Ну мне просто есть такая А подожди
another story about welfare You
ещё история про благосостояние Ты же
asked me again the same Cyprus
меня спросили опять же тот же Кипр
twenty-first
двадцать первый
year these consequences of coronavirus
год вот эти последствия коронавируса
Yes in the twentieth It started in the twenty-
Да в двадцатом Он начался в двадцать
first we arrived there We rested everything is fine everything
первом мы там приехали Отдохнули всё
seems to be fine where did I
нормально вроде как всё хорошо куда я
lose the thread of the conversation Where did we go
потерял нитку разговора Куда приехали
to Cyprus to Cyprus is also the European Union Yeah, right
на Кипр на Кипр это тоже Евросоюз Да ну
Cyprus This is already like that yeah yeah
Кипр Это уже такое ну да ну всё
anyway And when we were leaving they introduced
равно И вот когда мы уезжали там ввели
mandatory conditions to
обязательные условия раз в 3 дня
check all employees every 3 days Who works
проверять всех сотрудников Кто работает
in restaurants in public places For
в ресторанах в общественных местах На
coronavirus at their own expense of these
коронавирус за собственный счёт этих
people we didn't have this
людей у нас такого не было
horror horror what
ужас ужас
else in Poland
что ещё в Польше
Cool I won't say anything Everything is great everything is
Круто ничего не скажу Всё отлично всё
wonderful such a little bit I hope
замечательно такая немножечко Надеюсь
that also a little bit
что тоже немножечко
guys brainwashed propaganda
ребята промытые пропаганды К
Unfortunately the Poles Yes yes I asked one
сожалению поляки Да да я попросил одного
colleague I say show me some
коллегу говорю покажи мне какую-нибудь
landmark in sha
достопримечательно в ша
and so on Dale something like that what you were not
и так Дале тому подоб что ва не
located in we had
располагалось во у нас там располагались
children's sections in Sovetskoe Vienna children's
детские секции в Советское Вена детские
clubs kindergarten something else and so on
кружки детский сад что-то ещ и так далее
I go you are very lucky because we
я го вам очень повезло потому что у нас
lived in such high-rises  The state elite
в таких высотках жила Элита государства
And you
А вам
got it in the end And they are ungrateful yes it
пришло в итоге Да и они неблагодарные да
turns out
получается
Poles Yes all the same they are grateful to no one no
поляки Да всё равно благодарны никому
one should be grateful to anyone I mean that you
никто никому не должен быть благодарен Я
just need to analyze you
к тому что просто надо анализировать
need to think what is being done why Wait
надо думать что зачем делается Подождите
you came to Warsaw and something is
вы приехали в Варшаву и что-то
outraged
возмущается
that the Poles do not like this skyscraper And I was
что полякам не нравится эта высотка А я
outraged well you are somehow surprised if
возмущался ну вы что-то удивляетесь если
they live in this city they may know
они живут в этом городе они может знают
that they like it do not like it
что она им нравится не нравится
so I was surprised that they do not understand
так я удивился тому что они не понимают
they were told that it is bad As I understood It is
им сказали что это плохо Как я понял Это
bad nose You did not hear the Key ul
плохо нос Ты же не услышал Ключевое улл
this skyscraper was built for
эту высотку построили для
children for Polish
детей для польских
children not for Polish generals not for
детей не для генералов польских не для
Soviet you came from Russia to Poland
советских ты приехал из России в Польшу
in Warsaw saw a skyscraper that outraged you
в Варшаве увидел высотку что тебя
[ __ ] did not outrage me I was surprised that
гою меня не возмутило меня удивило что
you were
тебя
surprised surprised that they do not understand that this
удивило удивило что они не понимают что
huge
для них построили вот это вот огромную
maybe ugly history was built for them the last
может бы некрасивую историю послед
Soviet
Советский
Union The Soviet Union was built for the
Союз Советский Союз построил для
Poles
Поляков
Yes and who restored Poland Warsaw
Да а кто восстановил Польшу Варшаву
which was svna with zj after the war and about
которая была свна с зй после войны а про
I as far as I remember that  Russians say
Я сколько помню что россияне говорят
that they built everything in Estonia, they also
чтом всё в Эстонии строили они ещё и
built Poland, and you didn't know that,
Польшу отстроили а ты не знал этого
no. Cool, and I'm wrong about something. I do
нет Прикольно а а я не прав в чём-то Я
n't know. I just hear about it for the first time. I'm not
не знаю я просто я Впервые слышу я не в
aware of this. Somehow I know that the
курсе я этот момент как-то я знаю что
Soviet Union built all the factories for us in
нам все заводы и строил Советский Союз в
Estonia. It built all the nuclear power
Эстонии украинцам строил все атомные
plants, factories, ships, for the Ukrainians. It built for the Kazakhs. It built for the
станции заводы пароходы казахам строил
Azerbaijanis. Yes. And then there's also the po-pozh.
азербайджанцам да А тут ещё и по пож
Wait, who built it if not the Soviet Union
Подожди а кто ро если не Советский Союз
in Estonia. Cool. Wait, in Estonia.
в Эстонии прикольно подожди в Эстонии
Who built it if not the Soviet Union. Well,
Кто строил если не Советский Союз Ну
like the Russians built it or who. And
типа русские построили или кто А
how do you think? I think that the
както как ты считаешь я думаю что
Estonians who lived there built it, that's
эстонцы строили которые там
why it's not about Estonia now, that's why. But
жили вот поэтому сейчас не про Эстонию
this topic is close to me. By the way, I have a
вот поэтому А вот эта тема мне близка
lot of people
меня очень много есть
who worked there. There used to be
которые работали были такие раньше
trusts called bridges. After graduating from
тресты назывались мосто отряды их после
college, they were sent to build something,
институтов отправляли строить чего-то
somewhere, bridges, houses, and so on. That's how I have it, yes,
где-то мосты дома и так далее вот у меня
my father did it. Baikal, Amur, not my father,
да у меня отец так Байкал амурскую не не
but it
отец а
turns out that he is not my father, not Baikal,
получается как это не отец не Байкала
Amur,  it's me it's not Baikal Baikal
амурскую это я это не Байкала Байкала
Amurskaya I didn't build
амурскую строил у
it I didn't not Baikal Amurskaya it's me who deceived
меня не не Байкал амурскую это я обманул
standing on Shushin not standing on Shushin it's GS I won't
стоя на шушин не стоя на шушин это ГС не
tell my father now where they sent it's not in
сейчас скажу отца куда отправляли это не
short to Ulan-Ud to Ulan-Ud but it's not bam it's
короче в Улан уд в Улан уд но это не бам
not bam they built it's not bam it's just
это не бам строили это не бам это мне
in my head it's a tale Damn I can't say now what it's called some kind of Biskaya I don't know that's what I have I just in my head Baikal Amurskaya you know
просто в голове Байкала Амурская знаешь
how Oh with this peony it's not Baikal
как О вот с этим пионе это не Байкала
Amurskaya in general my father they are in Ulan Yes
амурска в общем у меня отец они в улану
they were sent from Tartu University as
Да из тартуского университета их
students and they built
отправляли студентами и они строили там
something there Well and I have a lot of
чтот Ну вот а у меня вот очень много
friends who
знакомых которые
built in Latvia there was some
строили в Латвии там был какой-то
Soviet Mostotryad and they
Советский Мостотряд и там куча всего
built a lot of things there and a lot of people stayed there and
строили и куча народу там осталась и
a lot of people then returned back to
куча народу их потом обратно вернулась в
Russia well that's
Россию ну это
my relatives neighbors live with and
вот с моими родственниками соседи живут
their children stayed there and you know the
а их дети остались там и Знаешь
last 2 years two yes last New
последние 2 года два да в прошлом Новом
Year it  they started to return en masse
году это началось они начали массово
from Latvia to Russia because they say Well
Россию из Латвии потому что говорят Ну
guys we are no longer citizens we are no longer
всё ребят мы уже не граждане мы уже
anyone at all super Well somehow I think
вообще никто супер Ну как-то я считаю
this is not very good because people
это не очень хорошо потому что люди
worked for the country built
работали на страну строили
something made roads and so on
что-то делали дороги и так далее
These people Yes made roads and bridges Latvians
Эти люди Да делали дороги и мосты латыши
made roads and bridges in the Leningrad
делали дороги и мосты в Ленинградской
region
области
Well Latvians
Ну латыши
la No Latvians who remained They live
ла Нет латыши которые остались Они живут
with them everything is fine they Whoever wanted
с ними всё хорошо они Кто захотел
got passports no one oppresses them everything is
получил паспорта их никто не гнобит всё
fine look I will tell you What is the matter with
прекра смотрите я скажу В чём дело с
Latvia in
латвией в
Latvia about 30% of the population is
Латвии около 30% населения - это
imported Latvians that is
завезённый латышей
my relative and
вот моего получается родственника и
Latvians were taken to camps And there they
латышей вывозили в лагеря А туда
brought Russians Ukrainians Belarusians
завозили русских украинцев белорусов
Kazakhs And so on and so on yes In order for
казахов И так дальше да Для того чтобы
30% of the population of Latvia to be the descendants of
30% населения Латвии это потомки вот
these occupiers it turns out yes in
этих оккупантов получается да в
1940 it turns out Latvia was
сороковом году получается Латвию
captured by the Soviet Union under the Hammer NT Pact
захватил Советский Союз по пакту молото
there was another story you have I
там была у вас ещё история такая Я
might be
возможно что-то
confusing something if I am confusing Tell me right away I am
путаю если путаю Скажи мне сразу я вот
not strong there I  only recently I started to get into this topic
там не силён Я только недавно в эту тему
I became
начал вылезать мне стало
interested and Kurland
интересно а Курляндия
is Kurland it
это Курляндия это
turns out look it included Latvia
получается смотри оно включало Латвию
so part of Estonia
так часть Эстонии
Lithuania I don't know in my opinion or was
Литвы не знаю по-моему или входила
Kurland part this territory was called the
Курляндия эта территория называла
Duchy of Kurland And another question
герцогство Курляндия А ещё такой вопрос
look when was the Russian Swedish
вот смотри когда была русская шведская
Northern War in my opinion the
Северная война по-моему
Russians in my opinion were there I don't remember first
русские по-моему там Я не помню сначала
they grabbed and
они отхватили а
then they
потом
beat me up in my opinion all the same all these
наваляли по-моему всё-таки вот эти все
Baltics became part of the Russian
Балтика вошла в состав Российской
Empire it was in the Russian Empire
империи она была вста Российской империи
in 917 when the Russian Empire
в 917 году когда Российская империя
sank into oblivion Yes then
канула в лету Да вот появились
independent Latvia Lithuania Estonia appeared Yeah well
независимые Латвия Литва Эстония Да ну
Listen cool I think you generally need to
Слушай круто Я считаю вам вообще надо
not demolish monuments to Lenin leave
памятники Ленину не сносить оставить
because he gave you independence I
потому что о вам дал независимость в
mean Lenin gave us independence we
смысле Ленин нам дал независимость мы
took independence ourselves Well of course we
сами взяли независимость Ну конечно сами
took it ourselves well
взяли хорошо
Hello Well how did Lenin
Здравствуйте Ну как Финляндию Ленин
let Finland go how
отпустил как
Well and how did he
Ну а
somehow let him in he was like let me let
как как-то подпустил он такой давай я
Finland go for example Estonia came
отпущу Финляндию например Эстонию пришла
Finland says We want to be separate
Финляндия говорит Мы хотим быть отдельно
Yes lady  said well and there was no war then yes the
Да ледин сказал хорошо и войны тогда не
same thing is obvious I don't know
было да то же самое очевидное Я не знаю
history in this mo here in this direction
истории в этом мо вот в этом направлени
look at February 24, 1918 the
смот в 24 февраля 1918 года был принят
act of independence of Estonia was adopted without any
акт о независимости Эстонии без всякого
Lenin and that's it it
Ленина и
was before that it turns out as
всё она была до этого получается в
part of the Russian Empire in Russia the
составе Российской империи в России
government changed not in Russia no a little bit wrong not in
правительство не в России нет немножко
Russia the
не так не в России сменилось
government changed and the Russian Empire
правительство а Российская империя
ceased to exist
прекратила своё существование
existence I agree it became the USSR and no no no
существование согласен стала СССР и нет
stop stop stop the USSR was created in 1922
нет нет не стоп стоп стоп СССР в 1922
then
году создался то
5 years after the Russian
через 5 лет после того как Российская
Empire collapsed here it became this new
империя развалилась вот стало это новое
State and then he comes and says I
Государство и тут тот приходит говорит я
want to leave you and this is a big
хочу от вас уйти и это большое
state which It is clear has a
государство у которого Понятно своих
lot of its own problems says go
проблем куча говорит идите
right And they could have attacked they could not they
правильно А могли напасть могли не могли
just did not have enough strength because Russia was
просто не хватало сил потому что Россия
then at war with Ukraine Yes and Yes so
тогда воевала с Украиной Да ещё Да так
that Russia simply could not simply
что Россия просто не могла просто не
could not Well I understood everything no but in any
могла Ну я понял всё не но в любом
case and did not pick and then in
случае и нарвать не стала а потом в
what year there three dem sor took
каком там три дем сором году взяла
its own but not Well what does it mean took its own
своё но не Ну что значит взяла своё
occupier she was she captured an
оккупант она была она захватила
independent
независимое
state Well what do you mean and  what do you
государство Ну и что в смысле и что вы
think is
считаете это
normal I think it is not very
нормальным Я считаю это не очень
normal but from a position of
нормальным но с позиции
strength atno from a
сильного атно с
position of strength Latvians e show these
позиции сильного латыши э показывают вот
e children of occupiers so that they get out
этим э детям оккупантов чтобы они валили
in Russia or from a position of strength I say do
в России или с позиции сильного Я говорю
not come to us in Estonia you are not
не приезжайте к нам в Эстонию вы тут не
needed here go to Baikal Yes from a position of strength
нужны едьте на Байкал Да с позиции
I say what from a position of strength because from a
говорю чему с позиции силь потому что с
position of strength because no
позиции сильно потому что вас тут вас
one is waiting for you here Jonas wait Let's
тут никто не ждёт йонас подожди Давайте
figure it out position of strength you are a strong
разберёмся позиции сильного вы сильный
person yes you personally and for you yes
человек да лично вы и для вас да спортом
play sports
занима спортом
So well here you go border Be
Так ну вот пожалуйста граница Будьте
Pskov region sit there Yes
Псковская область там сидите себе Да
forget about
забудь про
Ur that's what you Russian call it
Ур это вы русский её так называете
Urva
урва
Narva is not hot-tempered in principle not
Нарва не вспыльчивый в принципе не
hot But you know I specially When there is an
горячий Но знаешь я специально Когда
opportunity I will go to Narva and as
будет возможность поеду в Нарву и как
Zadornov our satirist Russian said I will give the
говорил Задорнов наш сатирик русский дам
taxi driver 20 dollars and he will sing me
таксисту 20 долларов и он мне будет петь
Russian folk songs Believe me Do you
русские народные песни Поверь мне А
know why Because in Narva there still
знаешь почему Потому что в Нарве ещё
lives
живёт
a little no So please don't call
немножко нет Так не называй пожалуйста
my nation it is not  I
мою нацию это не
call
оче называю Ну я
you Well, okay, it's
тебя называю
not the point, they don't swear And
Хотя ладно не суть сильное не ругаются И
even more so, they don't do such trifles, you
тем более вот такой мелочью не
know, I had an
занимаются знаешь у меня был у меня
observation Yes, I didn't do anything, I had an
наблюдение Да ничего не сделал у меня
observation
наблюдение
when you're on holiday in Turkey, there are
когда отдыхаешь в Турции там с тобой в
Balts,
отель заезжают и прибалты и
Ukrainians and Belarusians staying with you in the hotel Well, I understand, I misspoke
украинцы и белорусы Ну я понял поня
Sorry, I'm not wrong, so do
оговорился Извини меня уже не переу
n't worry if you come and
и не надо если ты на приедешь и в
say in Tallinn, you are Balts, they will catch up with you
Таллине скажешь вы прибалты тебе так
and you will immediately start talking to the Balts, the
поравняются и сразу будешь говорить
countries are a ball to me, so far in my life, no one is
Балты страны бал мне пока в жизни никто
evil and I think that this will not
нечисть и я думаю что этого не
happen while he brushes it off
случится пока отмахивается
Listen, what is it that they speak Russian
Слушай а что это они на русском говорят
with the Turks Well, when they check in, it is clear that Well, they
с турками Ну когда заселяются видно что
give you a Moldovan,
Ну они же дают там паспорт молдавский
Baltic, Ukrainian passport There,
прибалтийский украинский Там какой
any Kazakh you like By the way, I say so,
угодно казахский Кстати я говорю так
daughter, I am for peace throughout the world, I am telling you,
дочь я за мир во всём мире я тебе говорю
but here, simple Russian is an international
но тут простая русский международный
language,
язык учить английский
Ukrainians don't
украинцы не
want to learn English, Russians seem to hate them, but they speak
хотят русские типа ненавидят но говорят
NM And if they refuse
на НМ А если они откажутся от
it, who will understand Ukrainian
него кто же будет понимать украинскую
speech in the world, in Turkey, your Estonian, you
речь в мире в Турции твою эстонскую ты
speak Estonian yes yes you are at the
по-эстонски говори же да да ты на
resorts What language do you speak in
курортах На каком языке говоришь на
English In English Well
английском На английском Молодец
done learned here the rest speak Russian
выучился вот остальные говорят на русс
who does not
кто не
Vyra Inter poki I have
Выра Интере поки
not heard Poles very many speak
Поляков не слышал очень много на
English I
английском говорят
know but wait Poles in that What
знаю но подожди поляки в ту На каком
language do they speak Russian or somehow it
языке говорят на русском или как-то
turns out they do not have English and
получается у них нет на английском а
why can Poles I heard whom I
почему поляки могут Я слышал кого я
heard Yes why Poles will be able and Estonians will
слышал Да почему поляки смогут а эстонцы
not be
не
able that they will not be able Why Poles
смогут что не смогут Почему поляки
will be able to communicate in other than Russian at the
смогут не на русском общаться на
resorts And Estonians all if they do not
курортах А эстонцы всё если русского не
know Russian will not be able
будут знать не смогут
Well done Learn I am talking about something else Why With us I was
Молодцы Учите я про другое Зачем У нас я
born in the first year I
ещё родился в сет первом году я ещё 10
lived in the Soviet Union for another 10 years that is why I
лет пожил в Советском Союзе поэтому я
know Russian Yes I
знаю русский Да я ещё четыре класса
went to Russian school for four more years in Russia
ходил в ру школу русскоязычную
now our children Estonian they do not know
сейчас дети наши эстонский они не знают
Russian I have a son He does not know Russian and
русский У меня сын Он русский не знает и
I am fundamentally English in the first
я принципиально английский у первого
grade well done well done that is what I
класса молодец молодец вот это
support at least some international
поддерживаю хоть какой-то международный
language will be passed Not at least some but the language of
язык будет сдать Не хоть какой-то а язык
Byron Yes the language of Shakespeare because the
Байрона Да язык Шекспира потому что
Russian language is what is its essence Why
русский язык это в чём его суть Зачем
learn Russian if international
учить русский если международный
English if all Science in English
английски если вся Наука на английском
now all science is just in Russian
сейчас вся наука как раз-то на русском
Chinese and English and French
китайском и английском и французском
Science in
Наука на
Russian and you didn't know that you have science
русском а ты не знал это у вас наука
and you didn't know that we have science
есть а ты не знал что у нас есть наука
interesting well oh my goodness well oh well
интересно ну ё-моё ну
you understand I understand everything is a try You are
ё Ну вы понима понимаю всё проб Ты
a little bit here is America and everything oh America
немножечко вот Америка и всё ой Америка
look again I'll tell you
смотри ещё раз я скажу я в университете
I defended my dissertation at university all
я защищал диссертацию все
uh publications are done in
ээ публикации делаются на
English even Russian scientists
английском даже российские учёные
do publications in English Because
публикации делают на английском Потому
they need for citation then in
что им нужно за цитирование потом на
English buddy maybe some
английском дружище может какие-то
internal ones are published in Russian
внутренние у вас печатаются на русском
all international journals in English
все международные журналы на английском
scientific look buddy I'll
языке научные посмотри дружище я тебе
tell you this I'm talking about science Probably I went too far
скажу так я про науку Наверное я загнул
I'm talking about literature and about scientific
Я про литературу и про научные
research all Scientific research and
исследования все Научные исследования и
all literary really important
все литературные действительно важные
things in the world are translated into several
вещи в мире переводятся на несколько
languages ​​into English into Russian into
языков на английский на русский на
Chinese and French
китайский и на французский
other countries cannot afford
остальные страны не могут позволить себе
all these expensive translations and
вот эти вот все переводы дорогостоящие и
so on That's it
так далее Вот
even German is not translated
это са больш даже немецкий не переводят
I understand read
понял
open the sources of international
почита открой источники межд
physicists of the
у физика
modern No I don't  I'm interested in the
современного Нет я не интересуюсь
chemist
химика
Iago I have a different range of interests And I understood
Яго У меня другой круг интересов А понял
well, can you name some modern
хорошо а можете современного какого-то
Russian writer who the whole
писателя русского который знает весь
world knows whom the whole world knows I'm
мир которого знает весь мирчи Я тоже
not very interested in that either I read the
этим не очень интересуюсь я читаю
classics in short and now there's no one
классику короче а сейчас никого нет
why is it so obvious there is no well you're
почему так очевидно есть нет ну это ты
telling me and I studied I have nothing to say I have
мне говоришь а изучал мне мне нечем
nothing to say I don't study in
крыть мне нечем крыть я не изучаю во
Okay, okay And what about modern
Хорошо хорошо А что вот современное
Russe is exported to the whole world
Руссе экспортируется в весь мир
literature there is no science What what what
литературы нет науки нет Что что что
can we
можем
call literature there is what kind of you say no
назвать литература есть какая ты такая
I'm telling you I don't know but
говоришь нет Я же говорю я не знаю но
obviously it exists obviously means it doesn't exist we can't
очевидно она есть очевидно значи её нету
name it know this is very strange
не можем назвать зна это странно очень
conclusion Well for some reason Turgenev guns in
вывод Ну почему-то Тургенев пушки в
Tolstoy everyone knows this Yes she
Толстой это все знают Да она
really was Well yes and is there
действительно была Ну да а современное
something modern that is translated into English
что-то есть что переводят на английский
read into Spanish into Chinese
читают на испанский на китайский
obviously there is I don't know I'm telling you I'm
очевидно есть я не знаю я тебе говорю я
not interested in modern literature
не интересуюсь современно литературой
modern cinema cinema and lit what in general
современно кино кино и лите что вообще
Modern Russian is
Современное российское
exported to the civilized world the
экспортируется в цивилизованный мир
civilized world is Russia and China with
цивилизованный мир это Россия и Китай с
India with ancient civilizations And what do you
Индия с древними цивилизациями А что ты
mean in  mean Let's go to India and China
имеешь в виду Давайте в Индию и Китай
what is exported to India and China
что экспортируется в Индию и Китай
wait I'm now wondering what
подожди мне сейчас стало интересно что
you mean by the civilized
ты имеешь в виду под цивилизованным
world
миром
Let's go to Europe what Yes I mean Europe USA I
Давай Европу что Да я имею в виду Европу
won't say USA but Europe is those
США США не скажу а Европа - это тех
scumbags
жлобов
who did this in Russia like
которые так себя творили в России как
absolutely no one Barbarians they are
совершенно невио Варвары они
Barbarians civilization there is such an
Варвары цивилизация есть вообще такое
expression European Lisa Chinese
выражение европейская Лиза китайская
civilization let's talk about barbarians now
цивилизация давайте сейчас про варваров
Just tell me what is
поговорим Скажите просто что
exported to other countries Russia
экспортируется в другие страны России
what does it produce scientists what scientists
что она производит учёных что учёных
first of all what
во-первых какого
Hugo who is known I'll say this I have
Уго который изве с скажу так у меня есть
several ancient ones who have
несколько давних древних которые уже лет
been living in the States for 20 years they are
по 20 проживают вот в Штатах они
American scientists No they are Russian scientists
американские учёные Нет они русские
No they are American scientists they have been
учёные Нет они американские учёные они
living in the States for 20 years they are engaged in
20 лет живут в Штатах они занимаются
science in the States Yes they are representatives of the
наукой в Штатах Да они э представители
American scientific school they are
американской научной школы они
Americans sku brain buying was
американцы ску скупка мозгов была по
all over the
всему
world this is as you know for example a boy
миру это как знаешь например мальчик
came there went to boxing became a
приехал туда там пошёл на бокс стал
boxer from he is a Russian boxer No he is an
боксёром от он русский боксёр Нет он
American boxer also he is
американский боксёр также он
American if he  went Yes studied
американский если он поехал Да учился
there or for another 20 years he is there he is an
там на или ещё 20 лет он там он
American scientist already he is not a Russian
американский учёный уже он не русский
scientist what do you have here is a Russian who
учёный что у вас вот русский который в
lives in Russia They they feel themselves they
России живёт Они они себя чувствуют они
feel themselves Russian feel feel
себя чувствуют русскими чувствуют
Okay let's do it I am not strong in the
чувствую Ладно давай так я не силён в
topic that you raised but let's
теме которую ты поднял но давай так
take it from the surface yes yes right from the
возьмём с поверхности да да вот прям из
masses of sources I am
масс источников я другими вещами
absolutely interested in other things it is not very
абсолютно интересуюсь мне это не очень
important to me Well let's
важно Ну давай вот прямо
take it straight away weapons so weapons that are on the
возьмём оружие так оружие что на
surface yes yes what
поверхности да да что
weapons Well that's it Weapons That's what you what
оружие Ну всё Оружие Вот то что ты что
weapons let's do it like what kind of weapons do developed
какое ваше оружие покупают развитые
countries buy again let's figure it out What do you
страны опять же давай разберёмся Что
mean developed countries well what
значит развитые страны хорошо какие
Let's Name the countries that buy
Давайте Назовите страны которые покупают
your
ваше
weapons I am not an expert again in the topic But
оружие я не знаток опять же в теме Но
as far as I heard
насколько я слышал
India is one of the largest countries in the world
Индия одна из крупнейших стран мира
buys very cool Russian weapons
покупает очень круто русское оружие
What kind of planes submarines ships etc
Какое самолёты подводные лодки корабли и
etc how many
тд и тп сколько
submarines not just really Tell me
подводных не просто реально Скажи
how many submarines and ships
сколько подводных лодок и кораблей
India bought from Russia I am the same as you I don't
купила Индия у России я же те гово Я не
know I sometimes read the news I read the
знаю я читаю иногда новости Я читал
news
новость
that recently in  salon in India before
что недавно в салоне в Индии перед
some newest before testing the
каким-то новейшим перед испытанием
newest Russian before the demonstration
новейшего русского перед показательным
performance of the newest Russian
выступления новейшего русского
fighter the Americans took theirs off the
истребителя американцы свой сняли с
air because they admitted that it was
полётов потому что признали что он
cooler really like
круче реально как
zador Wait again are you
задор Подожди ещё раз ты на полном
serious now
серьёзе сечас
say some Russian
говори россий какой-то
fighter at an exhibition in India the
истребитель на выставке в Индии
Americans took theirs off because they realized
американцы свой сняли потому что поняли
that the Russians are cooler can you name can you
что русские круче можешь назвать можешь
name the brands of these fighters I don't
назвать марки истребители эти Я не
remember such things Read it
запоминаю такие вещи Почитай
yourself Okay, let's go if we've already started to
сам Ладно давай если мы уж начали
measure Well, seriously, don't look I
мериться Ну чтото серьёзно не смотри я
want Look, I'm just a supporter of
хочу Смотри я просто сторонник того
specific facts I was
чтобы конкретные факты меня как в
taught at university we should
университете учили мы должны фактам
operate with facts otherwise it's not clear what kind of self
оперировать а то непонятно какой самот
Understandable What source is it not clear what kind
Понятно Какой источник непонятно что за
in India I was known for you don't ask
в Индии я такое слыл тым не задаёшь
questions that I said I don't
вопросы в которых я сказал Я не
understand okay Which one do you understand
разбираюсь ладно В каком ты разбираешься
yourself Choose You yourself said weapons and then at Come on, let's say
ты сам Выбери Ты сам сказал оружие и тут
hello wait, come on, let's say
при Давай алаверды подожди давай
hello what Estonia sells to everyone
алаверды что продаёт всем
Estonia Skype and technology Yes at
Эстония Эстония Skype и технологии Да у
us Skype Yes Skype is Estonian
нас Skype Да Skype это Эстонская
development
разработка
was it is no longer fashionable for 15 years No well I yes
была это уже не модно лет 15 Не ну я да
Viber Estonian work use Viber
Viber Эстонская работа используют Viber
- It is only
- Это только
for does not use uses Yes and Japan
для не пользуется пользуется Да и Япония
bought those Yes what material what
купила те Да что материального что
material materially look we are a
материального материально смотри мы
Small country Yes here we are in comparison with
Маленькая страна Да вот мы в сравнении с
Russia We are not saying that we are the
Россией Мы же не говорим что мы там
world master there or so on Yes we have a
мировой господин или так дальше Да у нас
million population Yes but the standard of living in
миллион населения Да но уровень жизни в
Estonia is higher than the standard of living in Russia
Эстонии выше чем уровень жизни в России
we look at the neighboring Pskov
мы смотрим соседняя Псковская
region neighboring Pskov region Yes
область соседняя Псковская область Да
and the
и зарплата
median salary in the Pskov region is three times
медианная в Псковской области в три раза
not four five times lower than the
не в в четыре в пять раз ниже чем
median salary in Estonia minimum
медианная зарплата в Эстонии минимальная
also the same thing a second a second and prices and
так же самое секунду секунду а цены а
prices prices with us are not five times higher prices with
цены цены у нас не в пять раз выше цены
us I'll tell you more yes prices for
у нас Я тебе больше скажу да цены на
phones are lower with us in Russia prices for
телефоны у нас ниже в России цены на
phones are higher prices for cars are higher with you
телефоны выше цены на автомобили у вас
If you take a normal
выше Если вы возьмёте нормальный
car and not Lada Vesta yes then in the
автомобиль а не Лада Веста да то он в
Pskov region in Russia after
Псковской области в России после
customs clearance it will be more expensive than in Estonia
растаможки будет дороже чем в Эстонии
what kind of customs clearance are you in some kind of in
какой какой растаможки ты каком-то в
some kind of  you live in the nineties What
каком-то в девяностых живёшь Какая
customs clearance in stop European stop
растаможка в стоп европей стоп
European car is imported to
Европейский автомобиль завозится в
Russia it is to clear it in the
Россию он растамаживать
nineties no one imports it anymore
это девяностые годы никто уже не завозит
that everything is built here
что всё здесь строят
what in Kaluga here Volkswagen was with us in St.
чего в Калуге вот Volkswagen был у нас
Petersburg once I I'll tell you I'll tell you a
Питере раз я я тебе я тебе открою я тебе
secret you know how a car is made in Kaluga
открою секрет знаешь как в Калуге
parts are
делается автомобиль привозят части
brought in Parts are brought in and large Subassembly that's
Привоз части и крупно Узловая сборка вот
all it costs more than in Europe So that
всё он стоит дороже чем в Европе Так
means we can afford it Come on no Da You
значит мы можем себе позволить Давай нет
said about the prices let's
Дава Ты же про цены сказал давай сейчас
compare right
сравним прямо
now Come on name what
сейчас Давай называй какой хочешь
car you want to compare that you know
сравнить автомобиль который ты знаешь у
you have it on the coupon it's not a car
вас так в талоне продаётся не автомобиль
these are the cigarettes stop no no Where did you
вот такие сигареты стоп нет нет Куда ты
run off Come on car Come on car
убежал Давай автомобиль Давай
I bought mine
автомобиль я свой купил
now how much 4 years ago come on right now
сейчас сколько у 4 года назад давай вот
right now Name me
сейчас вот прямо сейчас Назови мне
some In which salon should I
какой-то В каком салоне сейчас
look now what car do you have I'll
посмотреть вот у вас какой автомобиль я
look at the salons there
посмотрю салоны там
Moscow with Well
Москвы с Ну
come on I don't know with Marina San some Well
давай не знаю с марини Сан какой-нибудь
what well Murana m come on
Ну какой ну мурана м давай
Murana Da
мурана дава
Moscow this is  that it's some kind of a
Москва это что какой-то он вообще
children's car Yes, why is it so small for children,
детский автомобиль Да почему детский так
there's a Nissan Murana, Central car dealership,
есть вот Nissan murana автосалон
something like that, Nissan Murana 2,
Центральный какой-то так Nissan murana 2
twenty-fifth year, 3.5 L,
чет двадцать пятый год 3,5 л
from 3.5 million rubles, it turns out from
ээ ри от 3,5 млн руб получается от
35,000
35.000
dollars, probably
долларов наверное
yes And what
да И чего
Yes, you're right Let's talk about
Да ты прав Давай теперь про
cigarettes now, damn And where do you live And where do you live, how much does
сигареты блин А у вас А у вас сколько
such a car cost here, you'll get it for 25,
стоит у нас такую тачку ты за 25
even on Easy
возьмёшь вообще на Изи
I Listen, Jonas, honestly, you
я Слушай ты йонас честно говоря ты
should be happy that with our low
должен радоваться что при нашем низком
standard of living and with our low
уровне жизни и при наших низких
salaries, we can afford to
зарплатах мы можем позволить себе
buy cars for that kind of money, and 3.5 is just
покупать за такие деньги машины причём
me, look 3.5 Most
3,5 это я так смотри 3,5 Скорее
likely not Well, I looked at it
всего нет Так я же Вот посмотрел
3.5 249 sha 35 You know Oh, listen, wait, stop, stop,
3,5 249 ша 35 Ты знаешь Ой слушай
stop, wait
это подожди стоп стоп стоп подожди ещё
again, I'm just looking at your
раз у вас я просто смотрю у вас
car, it's about one and a half times more
автомобиль приблизительно в полтора раза
expensive, 50% more expensive than ours, it's not even
на 50% дороже чем у нас это даже уже не
customs clearance anymore, that's why this is happening, I
растаможка это из-за чего вообще
don't understand, we can
такое с этим не разбираюсь мы можем себе
afford them  buy as a person
позволить их покупать как человек
in the Pskov region and here in Estonia well
в Псковской области и у нас в Эстонии ну
really we even gasoline If we look yes
реально мы даже бензин Если посмотрим да
like all the same our teacher will be able to
типа всё равно у нас учительница сможет
buy it more than a teacher in the
купить его больше чем учительница в
Pskov region how much in the Pskov
Псковской области сколько в Псковской
region Yes now I'll look just
области Да сейчас посмотрю просто
interesting Yes how how do they
интересно Да как как же в России
buy gasoline in Russia and now for a second I
покупают бензин и сейчас я на секунду
literally how do they buy
буквально как же в России покупают
gasoline and cars in Russia interesting with such
бензин и машины интересно при таких
low salaries did not think nose
низких зарплатах не задумывался нос
so
так
look
смотри
salary here according to gorodrabot ru the
зарплата вот по данным городработ ру
average salary of a teacher in Pskov for
средняя зарплата учителя в Пскове за
2025 is
2025 год
24642 ​​rubles that is 250 dollars yes they
24642 руб то есть 250 долларов да те
will write there
напишут там
know vacancies really
зна вакансии реально
vacancies teacher Pskov I I do not take there
вакансии учитель Псков я я не беру там
somewhere Siberia or Yaru stoni
где-то сибир или Яру стони
so like that teacher of physics and mathematics
так вот так учитель физики и математики
MBOU Lyceum of development Pskov from 25,000 to
МБОУ лицей развития Псков от 25.000 до
30,000 rubles so Teacher of technology MBOU
30.000 руб так Учитель технологии МБО
Lyceum of development Pskov 25,000 rubles teacher of
лицей развития Псков 25.000 руб учитель
mathematics also this lyceum of development from
математики тоже этот лицей развития от
22440 to  25,000 rubles 250 dollars 250
22440 до 25.000 руб 250 долларов 250
euros - This is the ceiling for a teacher, how do they
евро - Это потолок для учителя как они
even
вообще
survive? I didn't think about it. Wait
выживают я не думал подожди
a minute. I thought that in Pskov at least
я минутку я думал в Пскове хотя бы там
they have 400 bucks. In short, yes, this is
400 баксов у них Короче да ну это вообще
some kind of beggarly salary. Can you
какая-то нищенская зарплата
imagine? They buy them for this.
представляешь они их на это покупают
Doro. Look, there is even a
Доро Вот смотри даже есть учитель
primary school teacher, from 250 25,000 rubles
начальных классов есть от 250 25000 руб
to 40, up to 400
до 40 есть до 400
bucks.
баксов
I wonder, and also look at the prices in the
Интересно а ещё посмотри цены в магазина
Stop store. Pskov school number 11, a teacher of
стоп Псков школа номер 11 учитель
Russian language and literature, 242 rubles 190
русского языка и литературы 242 руб 190
dollars. Now look at the prices for
долларов теперь посмотри цены на
food. Go to the store on the
продукты зайди в магазин на сайт
Perekrestok store website.
магазина перекрёсток
Listen, if he gets 190 dollars,
Слушай если он получает 190 долларов про
what kind of prices can we talk about in stores?
какие цены в магазинах можно говорить
Go to the cheapest Pyaterochka. Then
Зайди в самую дешёвую пятёрочку тогда
how much does it cost there? 100. Can you imagine? 190
Сколько стоит там 100 представляешь 190
dollars. A teacher of
долларов учитель
Russia and cars for 6 million. Imagine.
руши и машины по 6 лямов прикинь
What kind of car does this Russian
да Какая машина у этого учителя русского
language teacher have? Well, what kind of car
языка Ну Какая никакая
will it be? It's just
будет это просто
awful.  oh yeah i don't believe that Well they
жесть капец Да я не верю что Ну они
survive at all No really look how is this
выживают Не ну реально смотри как это же
not invented 190 dollars salary of a
не Придумано 190 долларов зарплата
teacher of Russian language and literature in the city
учителя русского языка литературы в горо
can you explain to me what a person can
можешь мне объяснить что может человек
buy for 190 dollars a
купить на 190 долларов в
month I don't know I'm not familiar with such
месяц я не знаю мня такие не знакомы
prices I'll just earn a little differently Look
цены Я немножечко по-другому заработаю
I see our minimum
просто Смотри я смотрю у нас минимальная
wage in Estonia in the fifth year is 886
зарплата в Эстонии в д пятом году 886
euros That is if you have a teacher this is not the
евро То есть если у вас учитель это не
minimum wage the teacher gets it turns out
минимальная зарплата учитель получает
in
это получается в
Estonia the minimum is five times higher no not
Эстонии минималка выше в пять раз не не
p that's why people from your countries go to
п поэтому из ваших стран ездят в
Belarus for gasoline look again look again
Белоруссию за бензином ещё раз смотри
look again I'm explaining to you in
раз ещё раз смотри я тебе объясняю в
Estonia the minimum wage is 4
Эстонии минимальная зарплата в 4 с по
times higher than the salary of a teacher in
раза выше чем зарплата учителя в
Pskov tell
Пскове расскажи
me Du in Estonia are 4 times more
мне Ду в Эстонии стоят в 4 с по раза
expensive than in Russia I don't know what
дороже чем в России я не знаю какие
products are in Estonia but I know that all the
продукты в Эстонии но я знаю что все
guys from your countries went to
ребята из ваших государств ездили в
Belarus to buy gasoline and until they were
Белоруссию закупаться бензином и пока им
introduced
не ввели
there you want to say that we are from Estonia
там ты хочешь сказать что мы из Эстонии
through Pskov  we're going to Belarus for
через Псков едем в Беларусь за
gas Latvia Lithuania who wait
бензином Латвия Литва кто подожди давай
come on let's talk about myself look I don't know Latvia
давай я за себя смотри я не знаю Латвия
Lithuania I know I'm in Estonia now
Литва Я знаю вот я сейчас в Эстонии
from Estonia T again from Estonia you'll
из Эстонии Т ещё раз из Эстонии с тебя
pay a loaf of bread from Estonia look
стоит буханка хлеба из Эстонии смотри у
we have bread That's why all the
нас хлеб Вот почему-то у меня все
Russians ask me about a loaf of bread
русские спрашивают о Буханке хлеба
how many types of bread do you have
сколько у вас видов хлеба
Oh I don't know a lot that's it look
О я не знаю очень много вот вот смотри у
we have Well the most common yes look
нас есть Ну самый обычный да смотри у
we have from 15 euro cents loaves yes up to 2
нас есть от 15 евро центов булки да до 2
euros these are the kind of bread you can
евро вот такие хлеба какой хочешь можешь
buy any bread you want more more then look
купить хлеб больше больше то смотри
how much bread do you buy a month I
сколько ты хлеба покупаешь в месяц я в
buy three loaves of
месяц покупаю три буханки
bread a month no we love bread Often we have
хлеба не мы хлеб любим Часто у нас
because we have normal nutrition
потому что у нас нормальное питание у
we have meat Yes we have dairy in
нас есть мясо Да у нас есть молочка в
Russia in the Soviet Union double bread bread
России в Советском Союзе дабл хлеб хлеб
with butter bread with something else bread with bread
с маслом хлеб ещё с чем-то хлеб с хлебом
this piece of bread with a small piece of butter on it it's
вот такой кусок хлеба на него маленький
like a sandwich in
кусочек масла это типа бутерброд в
Europe they don't eat so much bread you
Европе не едят столько хлеба вы
constantly pay for this bread bread bread how much
постоянно за этот хлеб хлеб хлеб сколько
bread do you  how much bread do you eat a
ты хлеба сколько ты хлеба съедаешь в
month
месяц
loaves I don't know Well,
буханок не знаю Ну
about a little now I'm losing weight Well,
примерно мало сейчас худею Ну вот
how many times a day would you eat a
сколько даже раз в день ты если бы ел
loaf of bread it would be 30 loaves not once not
буханку это 30 буханок не раз раз не
No, just why are you asking about a
Нет просто зачем ты спрашиваешь про
loaf of bread if
буханку хлеба если
bread bread in
хлеб хлеб в
ny Let's have coffee lavaza Ora do you
ных Давай кофе лаваза Ора у вас такое
sell that I drink Americano with milk I don't know Well,
продаётся я Американо с молоком пью я не
I drink it like that I go to a cafe and
шарю Ну в зёрнах Я пью так Я в кафе
order I see How much does it cost in a
заказываю Понятно Сколько у вас стоит в
cafe in a cafe A mug of Americano coffee there are
кафе в кафе Кружка кофе Американо
absolutely different ones from
абсолютно разные есть
70 euro cents there are 30
от от 70 евроцентов есть есть 30
euro cents like different ones there are now
евроцентов типа разные есть сейчас
now Let me count 70 euro cents that's
сейчас Дай посчитаю 70 евро центов это е
15 euro cents there are it like
15 евроцентов есть это типа в
depending on Like how
зависимости от того Типа насколько в
cool of an establishment you are you take Well, in a
крутом заведении ты ты берёшь Ну в
normal one let's take the
нормальном давай так давай возьмём по
average taco chain everything is 10 euro cents
среднему тако сетевая всё 10 евро цент
if a chain coffee shop 10 euro cents is
если сетевая кофейня 10 евро центо это
how much 100
сколько 100
rubles in rubles how  100 rubles is not 100 rubles -
руб в рублях как 100 руб не 100 руб -
it's one euro will already be
это одно евро уже
like 10
будет так 10
rubles Come on
руб Да ладно
seriously wait not in a restaurant
серьёзно подожди не в ресторане
but like a normal coffee
а како нормальное вот такое кофейное вот
shop like this with takeaway coffee there
заведение там с кофе на вынос там
Some island in a shopping center where they have
Островок какой-то в торговом центре там
all the additives all the stuff you
где есть все добавки все дела ты
come there it's normal there I don't know
приходишь там нормально там не знаю
forget about our coffee or something
забей там наш кофикс какой-нибудь илий
like that well we have there A well I got it yes it
такое ну у нас там А ну такие всё понял
will be like that OTV euro
да такое будет тако ОТВ евро
itro rubles Cool We haven't bought from them for a long time
итро руб Круто У нас я давно в них не
but it seems to me
покупал но мне
rubles 200 300 I don't know by feel Well it's like
рублей 200 300 я не знаю по ощущениям Ну
this Look how we like how we
это такое Смотри вот как мы так как как
live such prices here with such
мы такие цены живём тут с такими
salaries well Explain to me
зарплатами такие ну Об объясни мне
look come on like this really I looked to
смотри давай так вот реально я посмотрел
teach we have a minimum wage the
учить у нас минимальная зарплата
minimum in Estonia since the twenty-fifth
минимальная в Эстонии с двадцать пятого
year 886 euros less just well the employer can't
года 886 евро меньше просто ну не может
pay yes that is average
работодатель платить да то есть средние
median They are already higher I don't
медианные Они и так выше Я не хочу
even want to compare a teacher from Pskov with a
сравнивать даже учителя с Пскова с
teacher from Pärnu but if we  let's see a
учителем с Пярну но если мы посмотрим
teacher in Pskov gets 190 dollars,
учитель Пскова получает 190 долларов
according to your estimates, how much does a
вот по твоим оценкам сколько на еду
Pskov person spend on food per
уходит псковского человека в
month, I don't know Well, what do you think, you
месяц я не знаю Ну как ты думаешь ты
know, it seems to me that this is some kind of nonsense
знаешь мне кажется тут какая-то ерунда
because I now
что у меня
receive a pension, but she really has an
ща получает пенсию но у неё правда там
additional payment, we recently talked about this topic, I
надбавке недавно мы что-то на эту тему
think she gets around
говорили по-моему она получает в районе
64,000, and now I'm raising it. Who is
64.000 а сейчас ещ и поднимаю Это кто у
your mother-in-law? 60,000 is your minimum there, the
тебя тёща 60.000 у вас минимальна там
north is the North. Probably it's the North. Yes,
север это Север Наверно это Север Да ты
first you work half your life in hellish conditions
сначала полжизни типа в адских условиях
and for this you get Well, there are no
работаешь и за это да получа Ну там не
hellish
Адские
conditions, a second,
условия секунду
such a pension in Russia is 12, I think,
такая пенсия в России 12 по-моему
thousand, I can't say here, in short, the
тысяч вот вот тут не скажу короче
main question is different, how are you so
основной то вопрос в другом нос как вы
rich with such cheap
такие богатые с такими дешёвыми
prices? You live normally, it turns out. And
ценами вы живёте нормально получается А
we are so poor with such huge
мы такие бедные с такими огромными
prices and such low salaries, we
ценами и с такими низкими зарплатами
buy cars for millions. I will say, I will say,
покупаем машины за миллионы я скажу я
look at the people who buy
скажу так смотрите люди которые покупают
cars for Milli, you and we have it,
машины за Милли он есть и у вас и у нас
but e  the average Russian is
но э среднестатистический россиянин
poorer than the average Estonian and
беднее среднестатистического эстонца и
that's why many Russians go to Estonia
поэтому многие россияне едут в Эстонию
now after 2022 it's
сейчас после двадцать второго года это
become a problem yes Because here Well they don't
проблемно стало да Потому что тут Ну не
really live and Before 2022
совсем живут а До двадцать второго года
I remember how many flies there were Yes really uh a
я помню как мух было у нас Да реально ээ
lot of Russians came registered
куча россиян приезжала регистрировалась
businesses opened moved here for
бизнесы открывали переезжали сюда на
permanent residence Why is it good and that's what We came to the conclusion that
ПМЖ Поче хорошо и това к чему Мы пришли
Estonia is cooler than Russia Well well
к тому что Эстония круче России Да ну
objectively the standard of living in
уровень объективно уровень жизни в
Estonia is better than the standard of living in Russia
Эстонии лучше чем уровень жизни в России
in the same neighboring Pskov region you
в той же Псковской области
can congratulate me on this
соседней вас с этим поздравить можете
congratulations nose you then it means you are
поздравить нос вы тогда значит вы
great everything is cool
молодцы всё классно
wonderful let's not take other
замечательно не будем брать остальные
examples Yes from life I don't really understand the history of
примеры Да из жизни я не очень в истории
modern
в современной
Estonia
Эстонии
But as far as I
понимаю Но насколько я
understand my personal
понимаю моё личное
impression is that you should visit your old
впечатление что вот посетить свои старые
places Yes of course you should But I don't want to live there
места Да конечно надо А вот жить там
Like a Ukrainian I'll tell you honestly
нет Як украинец я Тобе честно скажу
really [ __ ] you Estonia Estonia you would
реально нахуй тоб ця Эстония эстон тоб
n't want you to come there and
не хотели б чтоб ты туда приезжал и в
not to Ukraine either Glory to Ukraine you
Украину тоже не Слава Украине ты
[laughter]
[смех]
Ukrainian So you're Ukrainian So you're Ukrainian
украинец Так ты украинец Так ты украинец
So you're Ukrainian I spent an hour here drinking
Так ты украинец я тут час
Estonians I was telling them I was humiliating myself and you're
распил эстонцы Рассказывал унижался а ты
Ukrainian it was divine like
украинец это было божественно лайк
subscribe
подписка
comment and sit in your Russia you don't need to go
комент и сидите в своей России не надо
to Estonia or to Ukraine anywhere and
вам ни в Эстонию ни в Украину никуда а
all the people from Estonia just such a
всем людям из Эстонии просто такой
Divine Divine like Did you see
Божественный Божественный лайк Вы видели
how they rage Russia doesn't matter to them And in
как они беснуются Россия им по А в
Warsaw the USSR built everything for them Yes they built everything Yes the Estonians were sitting on the
Варшаве СССР всё Им построил Да они всё
stove
строили Да эстонцы сидели на печи
Ukrainians were sitting on the stove Poles were sitting too
украинцы сидели на печи поляки сидели
lying belly in Chukalin everyone everyone was
тоже лежали пузо чукалине всем всем
building Yes that's how it is but when he
строили Да вот так вот но когда он
heard something about the teacher's salary he blew
зарплаты учителя услышал что-то он дул
Because that's how it is if in Estonia
Потому что так оно и есть если в Эстонии
I was in Estonia in 2006 yes I
Я был в Эстонии в 2006 году да Надо
'll have to go again after the war Latvia
будет после войны ещё поехать Латвия
Lithuania Estonia but I saw we were driving
Литва Эстония но я видел мы проезжали
through Belarus and the Pskov region what the
через Белорусь и псковскую область какая
situation was there and what it was in Estonia it was
там ситуация и какая в Эстонии была это
visible to the naked eye and they were doing
было видно невооружённым глазом и они
something
что-то
there so if Latvia Lithuania Estonia
там так вот если бы Латвия Литва Эстония
weren't in  sovok these 50 years which
не была в совке вот этих 50 лет которые
sovok captured they lived even better
совок захватил они ещё лучше жили потому
because sovok stole from Latvia Lithuania Estonia
что совок украл у Латвии Литвы Эстонии
50 years from Ukraine Belarus stole 70 years and
50 лет у Украины Белоруси украл 70 лет и
other countries Kazakhstan Azerbaijan and
других стран Казахстана Азербайджана и
so on and now we are catching up with what
так дальше и мы сейчас догоняем то что
this sovok took from all of us When
вот этот совок забрал у всех нас Когда
Europe was developing Europe kept
Европа развивалась Европа шла
up with the times and here was
в ногу с временем а тут был
gulak piss piss
гулак
on my Telegram right now
пись пись на мий Telegram прямо зараз
axis VN
ось ВН
apok this is very and very important YouTube is busy with
апок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube заня
us through scarg ORV in your ban and very
нас через скарг ОРВ в твый бан и дуже
many videos I do not show people at times I do not
багато вдео не показую людям вчасно не
show information about streams so that
показуе информация про стримы тому для
we Mali operational links are
того щоб ми Мали оперативный звязок
written right now and Popik there in
пишиться прямо зараз а Попик там в
telegram okrim video also interesting and
телеграми окрим видео ще теж цикава и
useful information and we are obliged to you
корисна информация и мы повинни з вами
trimati constant operational links
тримати постийний оперативный звязок
independently in that chi will show you about this
незалежно в того чи покаже вам про це
YouTube  Glory to Ukraine
YouTube Слава Украине
write ah
пиши ah